dondengaeshi detatokoshoubu nerau wa ittou shou
An unexpected ending, deal with it as it comes,
we're aiming for first place
i can feel it donna toki datte hikari o shinjiteru
I Can Feel it, no matter what, I believe in the light
nigirishime ta yume ga koboreochi sou na
When the dream I've attained is
toki ni kagitte omoidasu no
about to fall apart, I remember
aitsu no ano yasashii kao
His kind expression,
mune no oku ga mata tsuyoku nareru no
the core of my heart is strengthened once again
bukkirabou no kokoro ni fire
My blunt mind is set ablaze,
gutto kuru ashita o tsukami tain da
I want to grasp tomorrow as it comes at me
mada mi nu sekai wa kowaku nai
I'm not afraid of the world I haven't seen,
shinji ta mirai desho hora let’s try!
isn't this the future we believed in? Come on Let's try!
kazoekire nai ano namida wa sou sa niji ni kawaru darou
Those countless tears, will they change into a rainbow?
osaekire nai kanashimi mo
That sorrow I can't contain
itsuka wa dakishime rareru ka na
Will I be able to embrace you someday?
yawa na haato ga uzukidashi tara
When my feeble heart begins to throb
arittake asu ni kisu shite ageyou
I give all of my kisses to tomorrow
furue ta mama no chiisana kobushi o tsuyoku mata nigitte
Still trembling, I clench my tiny fist tightly
dondengaeshi detatokoshoubu nerau wa ittou shou
An unexpected ending, deal with it as it comes,
we're aiming for first place
i can feel it donna toki datte hikari o shinjiteru
I Can Feel it, no matter what, I believe in the light
Hopes Entrusted to the Future
北ルート内には おられません。
He's not on the north route.
南ルート 西ルートにも。
He isn't on the south or
west routes either!
いったい我愛羅様は どこへ？
Where could Lord Gaara
have gone?
(我愛羅)大砂嵐は去ったようだな。
The massive sandstorm
seems to have passed.
我愛羅様！
Lord Gaara?!
何を騒いでいる。
What's the big commotion?
速やかに
二次試験を再開するのだ。
Stop making a fuss and
resume the Second Exam.
は… はい！
Yes, sir!
二次試験の再開準備を急げ。
Hurry! Prepare to resume
the Second Exam!
《フギ : ホウイチからの連絡が
途絶えて久しい。
It's unusual for Houichi
not to send a message.
失敗だったのか？》
Did he fail?
我愛羅様。
Lord Gaara!
フギ 一度ゆっくり話がしたかった。
Fugi...
I've wanted to have
an in-depth discussion with you.
して… 私にお話とは？
Well then...
What did you want to talk about?
俺は お前を砂隠れの大事な
同胞の１人だと考えている。
I've always thought of you as
a valuable citizen of the Hidden Sand.
むろん 今でもな。
Of course, I still do.
恐れ入ります。
I am humbled.
(我愛羅)かつて 俺にとって
同胞とか友とかいう言葉は→
In the past, words like "citizen"
and "friend" were just that...
何の意味も持たない
単なる単語にすぎなかった。
Mere words that held
no meaning to me.
生まれてから長い間
言葉としては知っていても→
For a long time after I was born,
even though I recognized these words,
実際には存在しないものだった。
they were not part
of my existence.
(フギ)ほう いつ その真の意味を
お知りになられたのです？
Oh. And when did these concepts
become real to you?
(我愛羅)崩すために入り込んだ
木ノ葉の里で→
When I infiltrated
the Hidden Leaf Village
with the intent to destroy it.
初めて友と言える人間と出会った。
There, for the first time,
I met someone I could call a friend.
皮肉にも それは敵であるはずの
木ノ葉の人間だった。
Ironically, he was an enemy
who belonged to the Hidden Leaf.
ソイツは俺と同じ境遇でありながら→
Although he and I
shared similar circumstances,
他人の痛みを
自分のものとして感じ→
he empathized with the pain of others,
and shared in their joy and tears...
ともに喜び ともに泣き→
俺は その男と出会って
気づかされた。
Meeting him made me realize...
友という言葉の大切さ。
重さを知ることができた。
how precious and important
the word "friend" is.
そして アイツのように→
And it made me want
to become like him...
誰かに必要とされる人間に
なりたいと思うようになった。
a human being who is valued
and needed by others.
我愛羅様は 今までも
そして これからも→
Lord Gaara, you are and
will always be,
砂隠れの里には なくてはならない
お方でございます。
a person who is essential
to the Hidden Sand.
今まで 俺は 恐るべき
兵器として必要とされてきた。
All this time, I've been considered
a military weapon to be feared.
それは 砂隠れの民にも 恐怖を
与え続けてきたことを意味する。
And that continues to instill fear even
in the hearts of the Hidden Sand.
そのような！
わかっている。
But that's—!
I know.
そうでなければ 父様から→
If this were not so,
my own father would not
have tried to kill me six times.
六度も命を狙われることは
なかっただろう。
風影への推挙を受けたとき→
I am aware of the deeply rooted opposition
to my tenure as the Kazekage.
里の中に根強い反対が
あったことも知っている。
受けるべきか
受けざるべきか…。
Should I accept position
or should I turn it down?
俺なりに悩んだが
木ノ葉の忍から→
It was a dilemma for me.
But after my friend, the Leaf Shinobi,
taught me about friendship,
友の意味を教えられてから
考え直した。
I thought it over and decided...
皆につけてしまった
心の傷を癒やそうと。
that I wanted to heal the pain
I had caused everyone.
しかし その思いは 砂の民には
なかなか通じることはなかった。
But it's been difficult to
get the people of the Sand
to believe that I am sincere.
俺がつけてしまった傷は→
There was a time I felt the wounds
that I inflicted on my people
もう治らないのかと
諦めかけたときもあった。
would never heal.
いっそ 恐怖とともに→
I thought I should just disappear
from the Sand Village,
その砂隠れから消えたほうが
いいのかもしれないと。
then the fear would
finally disappear too.
だが 砂隠れにも
何の先入観もなく→
But I found there were people who,
without any prejudice,
俺の思いを
受け止めてくれる者たちがいた。
accepted my feelings.
((お前は 自分自身に怯えている。
You are frightened of yourself.
武具を扱うときは
己の心を抑え 無心になれ。
When you handle a weapon,
you must suppress your feelings
and become emotionless.
(マツリ)は… はい！))
Y-Yes, sir!
((俺は 以前 木ノ葉で→
I once met someone just like you
in Hidden Leaf Village.
お前と同じような者と
出会ったことがある。
その者は 絶え間ぬ努力で
立派な忍となっている。
Through sheer perseverance,
he has become a fine shinobi.
(シラ お前なら
その者にも劣らぬ忍となろう))
Shira, I predict you will be
as good a shinobi as him.
その者たちは 俺を…。
These shinobi have to come to accept
and rely on my guidance,
そして 俺の教えを
必要として受け取り→
育んでくれている。
and are maturing steadily.
(ミコシ)もう少しで着くぞ。
We're almost there.
(ユカタ)でも まだ巻物
揃ってないんだよ？
But we still need one more scroll.
(ミコシ)まぁ いろいろあったからな。
Well, a lot of things happened.
今回は諦めて
中忍試験合格は次回に回そう。
Let's forget about passing
the Chunin Exams until the next time.
だったら…
巻物を手に入れることが→
In that case, I don't know
if we'll get a scroll,
できるかどうかは
わからないけど→
一度 手合わせしたい相手がいる。
but there's someone
I want to fight just once.
(ユカタ/ミコシ)えっ？
That person received guidance
from Lord Gaara
その人も私も
我愛羅様の教えを受けて→
忍として成長できた。
and developed into a shinobi,
just like me.
同じ教えを受けた２人で戦い→
There's something
I want to confirm
確かめたいことがあるの。
by fighting someone who received
the same teachings as me...
(ヨメ)あ～っ！ やった!!
着いた 着いた！
We did it!
We made it! We made it!
(シラ)だが 俺たちは
まだ天の巻物しか持っていない。
But we still only have
the "Heaven" scroll...
(セン)しかたないよ。
もう体力的限界。
It can't be helped.
We're physically at
the end of our limits!
俺が途中で個人的な戦いに…。
If I hadn't stopped along
the way for a personal battle...
そんなことないよ。
Don't say that!
そうだよ。 これが今の実力よ。
That's right.
This is all we can do right now.
きっと またの機会があるさ。
ありがとう。
I'm sure we'll get
another crack at it.
Thank you!
なんなの？
What is it?
シラ 私と戦ってほしい。
Shira, please fight me.
もし敗れたら これを譲る。
If I lose, you can have this.
(シラ)砂隠れ同士で戦っても
しかたがない。
It's senseless for Sand
to fight Sand.
俺たちは もう諦めた。
We've already made a decision.
あれ？
Hey!
これは必要ないものだ。
くれてやる。
This is useless to us!
Take it!
(ユカタ)あ… そうですか！
助かっちゃうな。
Really? You're a lifesaver!
ダメでしょ。
えっ？
We can't accept it.
え～っ？
What?
本当は 巻物なんかいらない。
Truth be told,
we don't want the scroll.
この機会に
シラと戦ってみたかった。
I just want to use this opportunity
to fight you, Shira.
俺と？
Fight me?
あなたも私も
我愛羅様の教えを受けた者だから。
You and I both...
have been taught
by Lord Gaara.
私たちが 風影…
我愛羅様の思いを受け継いで→
We are the ones who will carry out
Lord Gaara the Kazakage's will...
砂隠れの里を支えていく。
and support
the Hidden Sand Village.
その資格があるのか確かめたい。
I want to make sure
we deserve that right.
わかった。 受けよう。
Fine. I accept your challenge.
いいな？
シラが望むなら。
Is this okay?
If that's what you wish, Shira.
う… うん。
Y-Yeah...
ありがとう シラ。
Thank you, Shira.
その者たちとは？
Who are they?
それは 砂隠れの未来を
支えてくれる若い力だ。
The promising youthful power that
will sustain the future of the Sand...
俺は その若者たちを信じ
期待したいのだ。
I believe in them and
have high hopes for them.
俺の命を狙う者は狙うがいい。
Those who wish to hunt me
are free to do so...
しかし あの若い者たちを
巻き込んではならない。
However, do not involve those youths.
憎しみや
復讐の色に染めないでほしい。
I don't want them colored with
hatred and vengeance.
来い！ マツリ！
Come on, Matsuri!
はい！
Right!
自分は 風影に
ふさわしくないのかもしれない→
There were times when
I doubted myself as the Kazekage.
と 思うときもあった。
しかし 彼らと ふれあってから→
But after coming into contact
with them,
自分のような者でも
何かできることがあるのではと→
I realized that perhaps even
someone like me can accomplish things.
思うようになった。
そして 砂隠れの里から
憎しみを取り除き→
I want to erase hatred
from Hidden Sand Village,
同じ痛みを理解し合う
友と呼べる者たちを→
and create bonds with people
I can call friends...
Friends who understand and
share each other's pain.
つくるようにしたいのだ。
もし異議があるのなら
この首をとれ。
If you object, then take my head.
あの者たちを巻き込むな。
But leave them out of this.
あっ！
さぁ。
Come on.
ありがとうございました。
Thank you very much.
これを。
Please take this.
(セン/ヨメ)えっ!?
– Huh?!
ダメだ こりゃ。 アハハハハ！
This won't work...
《我愛羅様は成長された。
Lord Gaara has matured indeed.
我ら老兵が→
Perhaps we old soldiers
worried needlessly.
余計な心配をするまでも
なかったのかもしれぬ。
おぞましい記憶は
過去の闇の中に消し去り→
We must let the horrible
memories of the past
fade into the darkness...
あとは
次の時代をつくる世代に任せる》
And leave it to the next generation
to build a new future.
《すべては わし一人の責任》
I alone was responsible
for all of this.
(リー)これで
なんとかしてほしいんですが。
Please accept these.
２本とも天の巻物では ダメです。
Two "Heaven" scrolls
are not acceptable!
え～っ そんな！
Oh, but that's—!
ダメ ダメダメダメ！
No, no, no!
詳しくは言えませんが
我々には巻物を集められない→
I can't reveals any details, but there were
extraordinary circumstances
重要な事情が。
風影様に聞いてください！
that prevented us
from collecting scrolls!
Please ask Lord Kazekage!
どんな事情があってもダメなのです。
It doesn't matter what circumstances
there were. No means no!
ケチ！
(テンテン)まぁまぁ。
You are stingy!
– Now, now...
– Just give it up.
(ネジ)諦めろ。
だって…。
No...! I can't just give up!
諦めきれません！
(テマリ)三次試験を中止？
Cancel the Third Exam?
すまぬ。 詳しく
語るわけにはいかないが→
I'm sorry.
I can't go into details,
砂隠れ内部の事情だ。
but this is a domestic matter
within the Sand.
(シカマル)じゃあ 中忍昇進は？
Then how do we determine
who passed the Chunin Exams?
二次試験における各班の活躍を
詳細なレポートにしてある。
We've prepared detailed reports
about each team's performance
in the Second Exam.
中忍に昇進させるべきかどうかは
おのおのの里で決めてほしい。
I'd like the respective villages
to use them
to decide whether their participants
should be promoted to chunin.
まぁ もともと
中忍としての任務を→
Well, these exams were meant
to test their ability
遂行しうる力があるかどうか
確かめるための試験。
to carry out missions as chunin...
(カンクロウ)そういうことなら
しかたないじゃん。
It can't be helped if
things turned out like this.
(ガイ)しかし 魔の砂漠を
命懸けで渡った受験者が→
But the participants put their lives
on the line to cross the Demon Desert...
納得するかどうか。
Will they be satisfied with this?
わかっている。
I understand that.
第三次試験は中止らしいな。
Looks like the Third Exam
is cancelled.
えっ
中忍試験はどうなるんですか？
What happens to
the Chunin Exams then?
なんだか
やな予感はしてたのよね。
I did have a bad feeling
about this...
(キバ)ったく あの苦労の日々は
ムダだったのかよ。
Does that mean all that effort
was for nothing?!
(シノ)我々は 最後まで無事
たどり着いたのだから問題ない。
We continued to the very end and
didn't give up, so we should be okay.
問題は
途中で脱落したヤツらのほうだ。
Those who dropped out midway
are the ones who should be worried.
(ヒナタ)なんだか かわいそう。
I sort of feel sorry for them.
(チョウジ)腹減り損の くたびれ儲け
ってことかな。
All we gained was hunger
and exhaustion.
(いの)何にも儲けてないでしょ！
That's no gain!
(サクラ)でも 自信だけはついたかも。
At the very least,
perhaps we gained self-confidence.
受験者諸君 ご苦労だった。
Exam participants!
I commend your hard efforts!
時は流れ 忍の世界にも→
With the passage of time,
our shinobi world needs
a new system with new laws.
新たな定めによる
秩序が必要になった。
今まで忍は
掟のためなら仲間の命すら→
Until today, we shinobi were
required to sacrifice
犠牲にせねばならないと
言われていた。
even the lives of our comrades
for the sake of our laws and rules.
しかし 我々は今→
But I have realized that we have
something even more precious
規則より
大事なものがあることを知った。
than rules and regulations.
それは友であり
同じ里の仲間であり→
That is friendship,
with our fellow villagers, our fellow shinobi,
痛みを分かち合える者同士の
絆である。
and the bond we share with others
who understand the same pain...
今 ここに立つ諸君は→
I believe that
すでに そのことを
十分知っている者たちであると→
each of you who stands here now
knows exactly what I mean.
理解している。
よって 第三次試験の必要はなく
免除とし→
Therefore, I deem
the Third Exam unnecessary...
更に 第二次試験における
一部条件を解除する。
Furthermore, I am rescinding part of
the requirements for the Second Exam.
それって どういうこと？
So what does that mean?
今 ここに並ぶ諸君の
第二次試験の内容は→
For each of you standing
here right now,
詳細なレポートとして
おのおのの里へ送られる。
a detailed report of your performance
will be sent to your respective villages.
諸君の昇進は
里の影たちに判断してもらい→
Your Kage will make the final decision
on your promotion.
決めることとする。
え～ お預けかよ！
That means we have
to wait longer?
でも 僕たちにもまだ
可能性が残ってるってことですね。
But it also means we still
have a chance, correct?
北の国境に行ったら
体 気をつけろよ！
When you reach
the northern border, be careful.
ありがとう。
Thank you.
ヨメ 向こうへ行っても仲よくな！
Yome, since you're going up
there too, try to be nice!
えっ!? え？ え？
Huh?! What? Huh?!
ただ 偶然 任務地が
同じになっただけで…。
We got assigned to
the same place by chance, that's all!
いいから いいから！
Yeah, sure!
頑張れよ！
Go for it!
え～！ えっ えっ えっ？ え～！
(シラ)ヨメ 行くぞ！
えっ!?
Yome, let's go!
あっ ちょっと待って～！
Hey, wait up!
大丈夫か？ あれで…。
I hope they're going to be okay!
(小南)砂隠れよりのレポートを
検証した結果→
We've gone through the report
from the Hidden Sand,
お前たちの中忍昇進を認める。
and your Chunin promotion
has been approved.
(アジサイ)ありがとうございます。
Thank you.
(小南)早速だが→
And I'm going to assign you
to an S-rank mission right away.
お前たちに
Ｓ級任務を命じるものとする。
(リュウスイ)今日の死体は軽いな。
Today's corpse is really light.
(ユウダチ)長年の勘でわかる。
こりゃ女だ。
I can tell by experience...
this one is a woman.
俺たちが いつも死体を運ぶ→
The highest tower in the village where
we always deliver these bodies...
この里で いちばん高い塔…。
あそこが何か知ってるか？
You know what that's for?
だいたい この里では→
In our village, isn't it usually where
the ashes are enshrined?
塔ってのは
骨を安置するためのもんだろ。
もともとは死者の供養や
報恩のために築かれた建造物だ。
It was originally built as
a memorial to honor the dead.
なら なんで死者の身内まで
立ち入り禁止になってる？
If that's the case, why is it off-limits to
even relatives of the dead?
"NO TRESPASSING"
さぁな 知るかよ。
Like I know...
実はな あそこにペイン様が
いらっしゃるんじゃないかと…。
Rumor has it that Lord Pain
is up there.
へぇ～ そりゃすげぇ。
って そんなわけねえだろ。
Huh? That's ridiculous...
It can't be true.
噂だ 噂。
Rumor... It's just a rumor.
(リュウスイ)そんなことより
確認するぞ。
Anyway, I'm going to check it out...
お前の言うとおりだったな 女だ。
Just like you said, it's a woman.
(ユウダチ)中忍のアジサイ…。
It's Ajisai the chunin.
こないだ試験に
合格したばかりだってのに…。
She just passed the exams recently.
中忍になって最初の任務で
殉職とは…。
Her very first mission after becoming
a chunin... ended like this?
ご苦労さま。
あぁ 天使様。
Thank you very much.
Oh... Lady Angel!
早く 次を運んできなさい。
Bring the next one, quickly.
(ケゴン)ヨウロウ。
(ヨウロウ)あぁ さっきからだ。
Yourou!
I know... We're being followed.
フウ いったん あの岩場へ。
Fuu... Let's go to that rocky area for now.
(フウ)え？ しようがないなぁ。
What? How boring.
どこのどなたか存ぜぬが
とっくに気づいてるぞ！
We don't know who you are...
But we've been on to you
for a while now.
(飛段)俺は やめようって
言ったんだぜ。
I told him to stop...
殺せねえのは面倒くせぇしさ。
since not being able to kill you
is such a pain in the butt.
ねぇ そっちのおじさん
ひょっとして元滝隠れ？
Say, mister! Aren't you a former
Hidden Waterfall?
(角都)うむ…。
なに!?
What?
アッシ知ってるっす。
火影暗殺に失敗して→
I know you! After your failed Hokage
assassination attempt,
上役の心臓奪って里抜けした
角都先輩っしょ？
you stole the hearts of
the village elders and escaped...
You're Kakuzu!
角都!?
Kakuzu?!
Impossible! How old does
that make him?!
そんな 歳いくつだ？
I always thought if
I got to meet you,
アッシ 角都先輩に会えたら
友達になってほしかったっす！
I'd like to be your friend!
角都… アイツ バカか！
Kakuzu... Is she stupid?
さあ？ 里を抜けたのは
昔の話だからな。
I wouldn't know.
I deserted the village
a long time ago.
最初は お茶飲み友達くらいから
お願いします！
How about we start out as
casual acquaintances over tea?
今日 ここに現れたのは
友達になるためじゃない。
I didn't come here today
to become your friend...
それは残念っす。
Well, that's too bad...
(綱手)諸君の二次試験のレポートは
精査させてもらった。
I've gone over
your Second Exam reports.
その結果
ヒナタ シノ キバ チョウジ いの サクラ→
And... Hinata, Shino, Kiba,
Choji, Ino and Sakura...
この６人は
問題なく中忍昇格！
You six passed with flying colors
and are promoted to chunin!
《やはり 二本の巻物が
揃ってませんでしたからね》
After all, we didn't have
the second scroll...
コムギ 源内 イナホ。
Komugi, Gennai, Inaho...
お前たちは 次の機会に
譲ることとする。
You will be given another chance
next time.
あと ２本の巻物こそ
揃っていなかったものの→
Finally... although they did not
collect two scrolls,
その目覚しい働きにより→
they performed admirably...
十分に力量ありと
認められるため→
and are more than qualified
for promotion.
リーと テンテンは 中忍昇格！
(テンテン/リー)ハハッ… あっ？
Lee and Tenten,
you are now chunin.
綱手様！ 我々 ガイ班は
常に三人で一つ。
Lady Tsunade!
Team Guy is one for all, all for one!
How can Neji not be included...?!
ネジの名前がないのは。
最後まで聞け！
Just let me finish!
日向ネジは 二階級特進の上忍昇格。
Neji Hyuga is given a special
double promotion to jonin!
風影から
「ネジの働きは特に目覚しく→
The Kazekage himself noted,
"In particular, Neji's performance
was most impressive and"
特別に配慮されたし」とのことだ。
"due consideration has
been given in this report."
もともとネジは
中忍扱いだったしな。
He's already proven himself to be
more than capable as a chunin.
やりましたね ネジ！
おめでとう！
Way to go, Neji!
Congratulations!
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much!
２人とも
ありがとうございました。
Thank you to you both.
僕が中忍になれたのも
ガイ班のチームワークがあればこそです。
I made it to chunin because
of Team Guy's teamwork.
私たちのスリーマンセルは
永遠よね。
Our three-man squad is forever, right?
ああ そうだといいな。
Yes, I hope so.
I finally overtook Naruto!
ついに ナルトを追い抜いたぜ！
アイツ 中忍試験
受けられなかったこと→
He's going to be so mad that
he missed the Chunin Exams.
くやしがるだろうな。
ナルト君 今頃
どんな修業してるのかな？
I wonder what kind of training
Naruto is doing now...
《自来也 : そろそろ 修業を終えて
木ノ葉の里に帰る頃だのう》
It will soon be time to
wrap up training
and return to Hidden Leaf Village.
イテッ！ イテテ…。
Ouch!
(ナルト)ああ
まだ胸の傷が痛むんだろ？
That chest wound still hurts, right?
エロ仙人は休んでれば
いいってばよ。
Pervy Sage, you just rest up!
俺は修業を続けるぜ！
I'm gonna continue my training!
hitori ja nai yo
You're not alone
osoreru mono nante nai kara
There's nothing to be afraid of
ikou saa me o ake te
Let's go, now open your eyes
butsukatte ita
I was crashing into you
hontou wa oitsuki taku te
I just wanted to catch up so badly
kizutsuke atte
We hurt one another
tsunagi tomeru kizuna hoshiku te
I just wanted a bond to connect me to you
"gomen" wasure nai de
"I'm sorry" Don't forget
shinji te matte te
Trust in me and wait
mukae ni ikun da
I'll come for you
yuuki no tomoshibi terashidase yowa sa o
The light of courage, reveal our weaknesses
kizu datte itami datte wakeae ba heiki da
If we share our wounds and pain, we'll be fine
kimi no senaka osu musun da yakusoku
This is the promise I made you push you forward
itsu datte hanare tatte
No matter when, even if we're apart
shinjirareru kizuna wa mune ni nemutteru
The bond I believe in rests in my heart
Hang in there, Naruto!
What's going on?! My Medical Ninjutsu
isn't working on him!
It's probably because Nine Tails
has been extracted out of him!
But there's a way to save him!
That's why we're hurrying!
There's someone else where Sasuke is.
Do you recognize the chakra?
No, but it has
a real nasty feel to it.
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"On the Brink of Death"
Is this the end of the line for him?
美空ひばりさんの 『真赤な太陽』。
大月みやこさん
坂本冬美さんです。